Indiana University Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students, 1963-2017 C689
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students
1963-2017
2000-2016
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students
C689
8.4 cubic feet 15 boxes
The Indiana University Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students (IUHPFL) began operations in 1962 as an intensive summer foreign language and study abroad program for Indiana high school students. The program began with three sites, one each in France, Germany, and Mexico, and by 2018 had expanded to twelve sites in eight countries. The collection consists of administrative documents, promotional materials, teaching and instructional materials, and scrapbooks, ephemera, and photographs.
Access Restrictions
Advance notice is required for access.
The booklet "Saint-Brieuc, France, 1998" was pulled from the Student Projects subseries and is closed to researchers due to the presence of student passport numbers. Please contact the Archives staff for more information.
This collection contains electronic materials that require additional processing before they can be accessed. Please contact the Archives staff for further information.
Administrative History
The Indiana University Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students (IUHPFL) is a foreign language study abroad program for high school students from Indiana. The IUHPFL combines academic study of a foreign language with living abroad in order to emphasize both language learning and cross-cultural knowledge. Students admitted into the program spend five to six weeks during the summer living with a host family and engaging with the local culture. As of 2018, the IUHPFL featured study of five languages: Chinese, French, German, Japanese, and Spanish.
The program began operations in 1962, when David C. Munford, a former official of the Ford Foundation, approached Professor Merle Simmons of IU's Department of Spanish and Portuguese about establishing a study abroad program for high school students. Upon its foundation, the IUHPFL featured instruction in French, German, and Spanish, with sites in St. Brieuc, France; Trier, Germany; and Oaxaca, Mexico. In 2018, the St. Brieuc location was still active, with two more sites in France added in 1994 and 2010 in Brest and Saumur, respectively. The site in Mexico moved first to Monterrey, then to San Luis Potosí, and then in 2010 to Mérida on the Yucatan Peninsula. The site for the German program moved from Trier to Krefeld, Germany, in 1964, where it remained until 2014. In 2015, the German program moved to Graz, Austria.
In addition to the site in Mexico, the Spanish program also hosts sites in Spain. The first program site in Spain was established in the city of Valencia in 1996, with additional sites added in Ciudad Real, León, and Oviedo in 1999, 2005, and 2007, respectively. The site in Valencia was discontinued in 2013. In 2014, the program established its first site in South America, in the city of Viña del Mar, Chile. That same year, the IUHPFL also began a program in Chinese, setting up its first site in Asia, in the city of Hangzhou, China. In 2017, it began instruction in Japanese, with a location in Osaka, Japan. In summer of 2018, a program in Quebec City, Canada, will become operational, making it the fourth site in the French program. As of 2018, the IUHPFL operates twelve sites in eight countries.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into five series: Administrative, Promotional materials and publicity, Program instruction, Scrapbooks and ephemera, and Photographs. The series Program instruction is further divided into two subseries, Teaching materials and Student projects.
Scope and Content Note
The IUHPFL collection spans the years 1963-2017 and documents the office's work providing foreign language instruction and study abroad opportunities for high school students from the state of Indiana. Items in the collection document the administrative activities of the office itself, the teaching and instructional materials utilized in the program, and the personal activities and experiences of the student participants.
Materials in at least four of the program's languages of instruction are featured, as well as items from at least fourteen different program sites. Particularly well-represented are the sites in Brest, Saint-Brieuc, and Saumur, France, as well as those in Ciudad Real, León, and Oviedo, Spain. Types of materials include handbooks, evaluation and site reports, brochures, promotional posters, clippings from foreign newspapers about the program, group photographs, and scrapbooks. Other noteworthy items include instruction booklets with lessons in grammar, culture, and phonetics used at the program sites; end-of-session student projects; and scrapbooks and ephemera related to the Krefeld program.
Separated Material
152 loose photographs and eight scrapbook albums are housed with the Archives Photograph Collection. Most of the loose photographs as well as those in the scrapbooks are group photographs of the students at different study sites, but there are some candid photographs as well. One historic photograph dating from approximately the mid-1920s was also transferred from the Administrative series to the Photograph Collection.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory.
Archived web sites for this organization may be included in Archive-It.
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accession: 2017/138
Provenance
Transferred from the IUHPFL to the University Archives, November 2017.
Appraisal
Duplicate copies of materials were returned to the IUHPFL, specifically duplicate placement tests, newspaper clippings and articles, and copies of the video cassette "Indiana University Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students, Promotional Video." Additionally, foreign language materials that did not pertain to IUHPFL were returned, such as advertising brochures for foreign cities and tourist activities.
- Administrative, 1963-2017
  Scope and Content Note
  The Administrative series contains materials related to the general functioning of the IUHPFL office and the running of the program. Information about the selection process and placement testing is included, as well as handbooks distributed to the instructors, staff, and students. There are also documents related to student evaluations of the program, site evaluations, and the history of the program in Saint-Brieuc, France.
  Arrangement
  Items are arranged roughly according to the broad structure of the program, beginning with the selection process and proceeding through placement testing, pre-departure information, and post-return and general information. Within the group of handbooks, the general handbooks appear first and are in chronological order; they are followed by handbooks related to specific sites, which are arranged alphabetically according to language program, country of site, and then city.
  - Selection Process Summaries – General Statistics, 1979-2000 (Box 1)
  - Placement Testing Materials, 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Handbooks (Box 1)
    - Staff Guidelines and Instructor Handbooks, 2009-2012 (Box 1)
    - Staff Guidelines and Instructor Handbooks, 2014-2016 (Box 1)
    - Pre-Departure, 2010-2014 (Box 1)
    - Chinese: Hangzhou, China, 2015-2017 (Box 1)
    - French: Brest, France, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
    - French: Saint-Brieuc, France, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
    - French: Saumur, France, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
    - German: Graz, Austria, 2015-2017 (Box 1)
    - Japanese: Osaka, Japan, 2017 (Box 1)
    - Spanish: Viña del Mar, Chile, 2015-2017 (Box 1)
    - Spanish: Mérida, Mexico, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
    - Spanish: Ciudad Real, Spain, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
    - Spanish: León, Spain, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
    - Spanish: Oviedo, Spain, 2015-2017 (Box 1)
  - Excerpts from Student Reports, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation Report and Site Report, 2006-2008 (Box 1)
  - History of the St. Brieuc Program, 1963; 2001; 2008; undated (Box 1)
    General
    One historic photograph of a group at a wedding that dates from approximately the mid-1920s was removed from the folder "History of the St. Brieuc Program." The original was transferred to the Archives Photograph Collection, and a photocopy was put in its original location.
  - Correspondence, 2007? (Box 1)
  - Contact Information, 1999 (Box 1)
- Promotional Materials and Publicity, 1997-2015
  The series Promotional materials and publicity contains items created to advertise the program to students and their families. In addition, it contains items that publicize the program, such as articles from domestic and foreign newspapers and event pamphlets.
  Articles and clippings, as well as event pamphlets, are organized alphabetically by language, country, and then city.
  - "Indiana University Honors Program in Foreign Languages for High School Students, Promotional Video", August 1997 (Box 14)
    (2 videocassettes)
  - Brochures, 2009; undated (Box 1)
  - Posters (Box 1)
    - "Live Your Language Next Summer", 1994? (Box 1)
    - "Live Your Language!", undated (Box OS2)
    - Program Sites, undated (Box OS2)
  - Office signs, undated (Box 1)
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 1)
    - General, 2001; 2011-2012 (Box 1)
    - French Programs, 2001-2015; undated (Box 1)
    - German Program, 2008-2011; undated (Box 1)
    - Spanish Programs, 2004-2014; undated (Box 1)
  - Event Pamphlets (Box 1)
    - French Programs, 2009-2014 (Box 1)
    - Spanish Programs, 2009-2014; undated (Box 1)
  - "Oviedo 2009, Radio Recording of Interview to Students" (Box Ask Staff)
    (1 CD)
- Program Instruction, 2009-2016
  The Program instruction series contains items connected to the teaching and learning activities at different program sites. The series is divided into two subseries, Teaching materials and Student projects. The Teaching materials subseries includes booklets used by instructors for language instruction and covers areas such as grammar, phonetics, literature, and culture. The Student projects subseries features final projects compiled by students at the end of the program, with essays about their host city and letters of gratitude to their host family.
  Items in both subseries are arranged alphabetically by language of instruction, country, and then city. Within each city, materials are arranged chronologically.
  Access Restrictions
  In the Student projects subseries, the booklet "Saint-Brieuc, France, 1998" has been pulled due to the presence of student passport numbers. It is closed to researchers.
  - Teaching Materials, 2011-2016
    - Chinese, 2011 (Box 2)
      (3 folders)
    - Chinese, undated (Box 2)
    - Chinese: Hangzhou, China (Box 2)
      - 2014 (Box 2)
        (2 folders)
      - 2015 (Box 2)
      - 2016 (Box 3)
    - French: Brest, France (Box 3)
      - 2014 (Box 3)
      - 2015 (Box 3)
      - 2016 (Box 3)
    - French: Saint-Brieuc, France (Box 4)
      - 2014 (Box 4)
      - 2015 (Box 4)
      - 2016 (Box 4)
        (folder 1 of 3)
      - 2016 (Box 5)
        (folders 2-3)
    - French: Saumur, France (Box 5)
      - 2014 (Box 5)
      - 2015 (Box 5)
        (folders 1-2)
      - 2015 (Box 6)
        (folder 3)
      - 2016 (Box 6)
    - German: Graz, Austria (Box 6)
      - 2015 (Box 6)
      - 2016 (Box 6)
        (folder 1)
      - 2016 (Box 7)
        (folder 2)
    - German: Krefeld, Germany (Box 7)
      - "Krefeld 2009, Deutsche Musik" (Box Ask Staff)
      - 2013 (Box 7)
      - 2014 (Box 7)
    - Spanish: Viña del Mar, Chile (Box 7)
      - 2014 (Box 7)
      - 2015 (Box 7)
      - 2015 (Box 8)
      - 2016 (Box 8)
    - Spanish: Mérida, Mexico (Box 8)
      - 2013 (Box 8)
      - 2014 (Box 8)
      - 2015 (Box 9)
      - 2016 (Box 9)
    - Spanish: Ciudad Real, Spain (Box 9)
      - 2014 (Box 9)
      - 2014 (Box 10)
      - 2015 (Box 10)
      - 2016 (Box 10)
    - Spanish: León, Spain (Box 10)
      - 2014 (Box 10)
      - 2015 (Box 11)
    - Spanish: Oviedo, Spain (Box 11)
      - 2014 (Box 11)
      - 2015 (Box 11)
      - 2015 (Box 12)
      - 2016 (Box 12)
  - Student Projects, 1987-2016
    - Chinese: Hangzhou, China, 2015 (Box 12)
    - French: Brest, France (Box 12)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 12)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 12)
      - 2000-2002 (Box 12)
      - 2003 (Box 12)
      - 2004-2005 (Box 12)
      - 2007-2008 (Box 13)
      - 2010-2011 (Box 13)
      - 2012-2014 (Box 13)
      - 2015 (Box 13)
    - French: Saint-Brieuc, France (Box 13)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 13)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 13)
      - 1992-1994 (Box 13)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 13)
      - 1997 (Box 13)
      - 1998 (Box 14)
        (RESTRICTED)
      - 1999-2001 (Box 13)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 13)
      - 2004-2006 (Box 13)
      - 2007-2008 (Box 13)
      - 2009 (Box 13)
      - 2010-2011 (Box 13)
      - 2012-2013 (Box 13)
      - 2014 (Box 13)
      - 2015 (Box 13)
    - French: Saumur, France (Box 13)
      - 2010-2012 (Box 13)
      - 2013-2014 (Box 13)
      - 2015 (Box 13)
    - German: Graz, Austria, 2015 (Box 13)
    - German: Krefeld, Germany (Box 13)
      - 1999 (Box 13)
      - 2005 (Box 13)
      - 2012-2013 (Box 13)
    - Spanish: Mérida, Mexico (Box 13)
      - 2011-2013 (Box 13)
      - 2015 (Box 13)
    - Spanish: San Luis Potosí, Mexico, 2010 (Box 13)
    - Spanish: Ciudad Real, Spain (Box 13)
      - 2002-2004 (Box 13)
      - 2005-2006 (Box 13)
      - 2007-2008 (Box 13)
      - 2009 (Box 13)
      - 2010 (Box 13)
      - 2011 (Box 14)
      - 2012 (Box 14)
      - 2013 (Box 14)
      - 2014 (Box 14)
      - 2015 (Box 14)
      - undated (Box 14)
    - Spanish: León, Spain (Box 14)
      - 2006 (Box 14)
      - 2009-2010 (Box 14)
      - 2011-2012 (Box 14)
      - 2013 (Box 14)
      - 2014-2015 (Box 14)
      - 2016 (Box 14)
    - Spanish: Oviedo, Spain (Box 14)
      - 2007, 2009 (Box 14)
      - 2010 (Box 14)
      - 2011-2012 (Box 14)
      - 2014 (Box 14)
      - 2015 (Box 14)
    - Spanish: Valencia, Spain, 2006-2013 (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1963-2007, undated
  The series Scrapbooks and ephemera contains materials related to the German program in Krefeld, Germany, as well as scrapbook albums from various program sites. Items documenting the Krefeld program include handmade scrapbooks with photographs and ephemera such as tickets, maps, and clippings. There are also booklets, programs, correspondence, and other documents. The scrapbook albums contain mostly group and candid photographs, but also clippings and other ephemera.
  Materials connected to the program in Krefeld were titled "Mementos—Krefeld" by the IUHPFL office, and that title has been retained. The folders in this group have been kept in the original order as received from the IUHPFL office. The scrapbook albums are listed alphabetically first by country, then when necessary by city within a country.
  All scrapbook albums are housed with the Archives Photograph Collection. Contact Archives staff for more information.
  - "Mementos—Krefeld" (Box 14)
    - 1963 (Box 14)
    - 1965 (Box 14)
    - 1978 (Box 14)
    - 1979 (Box 14)
    - 1980 (Box 14)
    - 1981 (Box 14)
    - 1982 (Box 14)
    - 1983 (Box 14)
    - 1984 (Box 14)
    - 1985 (Box 14)
    - 1986 (Box 14)
    - 1987 (Box 14)
    - 1988 (Box 14)
    - 1992 (Box 14)
    - 2006 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1963; 1973; 1988; 1992; undated (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook Albums (Box Ask Staff)
    - Brest, France, 1994-2007, undated loose photos (Box Ask Staff)
    - Saint-Brieuc, France, 1963-2005 (Box Ask Staff)
    - Krefeld, Germany, 1966-1998 (Box Ask Staff)
    - Krefeld, Germany, 2000-2006, undated (Box Ask Staff)
    - San Luis Potosí, Mexico, 1970-2007 (Box Ask Staff)
    - San Luis Potosí, Mexico, undated (Box Ask Staff)
    - Ciudad Real, Spain, 1999-2007 (Box Ask Staff)
    - Valencia, Spain, 2000-2002 (Box Ask Staff)
- Photographs, 1993-2014 (Box Ask Staff)
  The Photographs series contains 151 loose photographs, most of which are group photographs of the student participants in the program. Other photographs include candid shots; street scenes; landscapes; photographs of a bullfight and other events; and a group photograph of students with the municipal president of San Luis Potosí, Mexico. All of the photographs are housed with the Archives Photograph collection. Contact Archives staff for more information.